A Guide to the Papers of Parker T. Hart 1932-1998
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
{Special Collections, University of Virginia Library}
Papers of Parker T. Hart 1932-1998
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11477
ca. 650 (9 Hollinger boxes, ca. 4 linear feet)
This collection consists of the papers of Parker Thompson Hart (1910-1997), former United States Ambassador to Turkey, Kuwait, and Saudi Arabia, linguist and author, ca. 650 items (9 Hollinger boxes, ca. 4 linear feet), ca. 1932-1998. These papers refer to the Middle East policy of the United States and leaders of the region, and contain personal correspondence, correspondence about Hart's career and the publication of his book, Saudi Arabia and the United States, articles by Parker T. Hart and other authors, copies of Presidential correspondence about the Middle East, a manuscript by Thomas C. Barger entitled "Out in the Blue-Letters from Arabia 1937-1940," interviews, and "The History of the United States Consulate General Dhahran, Saudi Arabia" by Kay Hardy Campbell. Other papers include biographical information about Hart, research papers and notes, newspaper clippings, newspapers, magazines, numerous maps, a scrapbook, itineraries, newsletters, information concerning oil companies in the area, and post Desert Storm literature. Items in the collection are in Arabic, Turkish, and English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Mrs. Parker T. Hart, Washington, D.C., on February 23, 1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
Parker T. Hart was born in Medford, Massachusetts, and graduated from Dartmouth College (1933), received a master's degree from Harvard in 1935, and studied at the Graduate Institute of International Studies in Geneva. In 1952 he also graduated form the National War College. In 1949, Hart married Jane Constance Smiley, of Washington, and they had two daughters, Margaret Hart Espey and Judith Hart Halsema.
Hart served in the State Department's Foreign Service for thirty-one years, entering government service in 1937 as a translator of French with the Department of State and being commissioned in the Foreign Service the following year. His first foreign posting took him to Vienna, where he witnessed the Nazi annexation of Austria and helped Jews fleeing to the United States and Palestine. During World War II, Hart served in Brazil where he investigated possible Nazi operations.
In 1944, his career turned towards the Middle East when he opened the first United States consulate in Dhahran, Saudi Arabia, serving as consul general from 1949-1951. Other positions related to the Middle East include: Consul, Dhahran (1945-1946); Service in the Division of Foreign Service Planning, Department of State (1947-1949); Director of the Office of Near Eastern Affairs (1952-1953); Deputy Chief of Mission, Cairo (1955-1958); Minister to Syria during the first months of the United Arab Republic (1958); Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs (1958-1961); Ambassador to Saudi Arabia (1961-1965), and concurrently Minister to Yemen (1961-1962) and Ambassador to Kuwait (1962-1963); Ambassador to Turkey (1965- 1968); and Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs (1968- 1969).
From 1969 until 1973, he was president of the Middle East Institute. From 1972 until 1990, Hart worked as a consultant with Bechtel Corportation. He is also the author of two books, Two NATO Allies at the Threshold of War(1990) and Saudi Arabia and the United States Birth of a Security Partnership(1998). For more biographical information, please see the biographical folder in Box 2.
Scope and Content Information
The Parker T. Hart collection consists of papers generated by his diplomatic assignments to Turkey, Kuwait, and Saudi Arabia.
The papers contain personal and business correspondence, manuscripts, research papers, magazines, newspapers, newsletters, clippings, a scrapbook, itineraries, information concerning oil companies in the area, maps, interviews including oral history interview for the John F. Kennedy Library, and photographs.
Correspondence discusses Hart's career; Thomas C. Barger; Saudi Arabia, King Ibn Saud, and King Faisal; Palestine and Saudi Arabian security; Hart's book "Saudi Arabia and the United States," an ARAMCO reunion; and the history of the American embassy in Kuwait.
Topics found in various publications, papers and reports include the 1945 Suez meeting between Roosevelt and ibn Saud; the Jordan crisis and Dhahran negotiations of 1957-58; Saudi Arabia; Kuwait; Syria; Turkey; Yemen; and the Gulf War.
In addition the collection contains the manuscript of Thomas C. Barger's "Out in the Blue-Letters from Arabia 1937-1940," and several reprints or copies of articles on the Middle East including Leonard Binder's "Transformations in the Middle Eastern subordinate system after 1967," Kay Hardy Campbell's History of the United States Consulate General Dhahran, Saudi Arabia," Sister Ann C. Coffey's (moderator) "Changing patterns of power in the Persian Gulf," Hart's "Reflections on Saudi Arabia," "U.S. policy in the Middle East," "Kuwait and the Saudi Security System," Chapter 8 of "Saudi Arabia and the United States," and "The view from Riyadh," as well as his electronic dialogue "Fifty years of Saudi Arabian-American cooperation."
Also Harry N. Howard's "Entry of Turkey into World War II," Kemal H. Karpat's Ideology in Turkey after the Revolution of 1960," John S. Keating's "Mission to Mecca (re a meeting between ibn Saud and F.D.R.)," Nasri Khattar's Litteracy for the millions," Douglas Little's "From even-handed to empty-handed: JFK, Nasser and the Middle East, 1961-1963," Christopher McMullan's "Resolution of the Yemen Crisis, 1963," Joyce L. Miller's Syrian revolt of 1925," Itamar Rabinowitz's "Syria's quest for a regional role," George Rentz's "Early years of the Saudi state, "Roger R. Trask's "Joseph C. Grew and Turco-American Rapprochement 1927- 1932," and Brooks Wrampelmeier's "Saudi hegemony in the Arabian peninsula."
Contents List
- "America and the Middle East" from the Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science1972 May (Box 1)
- "An American Policy Toward the Middle East" from the Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science[1970 Jul] (Box 1)
- American-Turkish Organizations Publications 1984 Nov-1990 Mar (Box 1)
- Arabian Peninsula Articles 1976 Nov 26-1987 Jul 6 (Box 1)
- "The Arabian Sun" Newsletters 1945 Nov 25-1995 Mar (Box 1)
- Arabic Printed Document (Unidentified) n.d. (Box 1)
- Aramco World Special Issue "Arabia the Beautiful" 1965 Sept-Oct (Box 1)
- Archaeology and Architecture of the Middle East 1964 Feb-1985 Aug (Box 1)
- Articles on Israeli-Turkish Relations 1980-1986 (Box 1)
- Articles on Jewish Citizens of Turkey 1987-1991 (Box 1)
- Articles on Persian Gulf Security 1969-1970 (Box 1)
- Background Material on Cyprus for "Two NATO Allies on the Threshold of War" 1977-1988 (Box 1)
- Bahrain Reports and Journals 1946-1977 (Box 1)
- Thomas C. Barger Manuscript, "Out in the Blue--Letters from Arabia 1937-1940" ca. 1986 (Box 1)
- Biographical material re Foreign Government Officials and Colleagues of Parker T. Hart 1959-1994 (Box 2)
- Biographical material re Parker T. Hart and Jane Hart n.d. (Box 2)
- Bibliographies of Books on the Middle East 1967, 1975 (Box 2)
- Brochure for Robert College in Istanbul, Turkey 1938 (Box 2)
- Brochure on American Colleges in the Near East n.d. (Box 2)
- Chronology of U.S. Air Force Base Rights at Dhahran 1992 Feb 17 (Box 2)
- Civl Engineering"The Kuwait Rehab: Up in Smoke?" 1991 Sep (Box 2)
- Correspondence and articles re Thomas C. Barger (1909-1986) 1986 Jul 2-1987 Jul 10 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Franklin D. Roosevelt re Saudi Arabia and King Abdul Aziz ibn Saud--copies from the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park, New York 1936 Nov 6-1945 Sep 7 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Harry S. Truman re Palestine and Saudi Arabian Security--Copies from the Harry S. Truman Library, Independence, Missouri 1946 Nov 6-1952 Apr 24 (Box 2)
- Correspondence re ARAMCO reunion 1983 Dec 8-1987 Jul 25 (Box 2)
- Correspondence re the history of the American Embassy in Kuwait 1988 Sep 18-Oct 25 (Box 2)
- Correspondence re "The History of the United States Consulate General, Dhahran, Iran" by Kay Hardy Campbell 1984 Nov 4-1992 Jun 1 (Box 2)
- Correspondence re Parker T. Hart's transfer from Dhahran to Washington, D.C. 1946 Jul 24-Nov 21 (Box 2)
- Correspondence from Tom R. McHale re the possible author of an unpublished biography of King Faisal 1979 Mar-Jun (Box 2)
- Correspondence re the publication and promotion of Saudi Arabia and the United States by Parker T. Hart 1990 Apr 9-1998 Dec 23, n.d. (Box 2-3)
- Correspondence with Turkish Embassy in Washington, D.C. 1992 Aug 26-1995 Jan 23 (Box 3)
- Diplomatic Service Administrative Papers 1941 Dec 22-1961 Sep 25 (Box 3)
- Documents concerning U.S. relations with Muscat and Oman 1942 Jun 13-Nov 4 (Box 3)
- "The Entry of Turkey into World War II" by Harry N. Howard 1967 (Box 3)
- George Washington Law Review Volume 22 Symposium on Muslim Law 1953 Dec (Box 3)
- "The History of the United States Consulate General Dhahran, Saudi Arabia" by Kay Hardy Campbell 1988 (Box 3)
- "The History of the United States Consulate General Dhahran, Saudi Arabia" by Kay Hardy Campbell 1989 Mar (Box 3)
- "Ideology in Turkey After the Revolution of 1960: Nationalism and Socialism" by Kemal H. Karpat 1965 (Box 3)
- Interview with Glen F. Brown regarding Saudi Arabia 1985 Nov 4 (Box 3)
- Interview in Al-Riyadh Newspaper (in Arabic) 1985 Oct 26 (Box 3)
- Jedda Agreement Text for the Settlement of the Yemen Dispute 1965 [Apr 10] (Box 3)
- "Joseph C. Grew and Turco-American Rapprochement 1927-1932" by Roger R. Trask 1967 (Box 3)
- "Kuwait and the Saudi Security System" Chapter Four Draft 1994 Apr 22 (Box 4)
- Lecture Notes for Foreign Service Institute Class 1983 May 24-1995 Mar 27 (Box 4)
- "Literacy for the Millions: Unified Arabic" by Nasri Khattar 1952 (Box 4)
- Maps--Aden 1949 (Box 4)
- Maps--Arabian Gulf, Arabian Sea & Environs 1949 (Box 4)
- Maps--Arabian Peninsula 1949, 1957, n.d. (Box 4)
- Maps--Bahrain 1949 (Box 4)
- Maps--Egypt & the Arabian Peninsula n.d. (Box 4)
- Maps--Egypt (Lower) & the Faiyum (in Arabic & English) n.d. (Box 4)
- Maps--Kuwait 1949 (Box 4)
- Maps--Red Sea & Environs 1949 (Box 4)
- Maps--Saudi Arabia 1949, 1960-1961, n.d. (Box 4)
- Maps--Saudi Arabia, City of Jidda 1949, n.d. (Box 4)
- Maps--South Arabian Federation n.d. (Box 4)
- Maps--Syria 1958, 1967, n.d. (Box 4)
- Maps--Transparencies of the Middle East, Turkey & the World n.d. (Box 4)
- Maps--Turkey 1945, 1966, 1973, n.d. (Box 4)
- Maps--United Arab Emirates (Arabic & English) 1973 (Box 5)
- Maps--Yemen 1961, n.d. (Box 5)
- "Meed Special Report" regarding Kuwaiti reconstruction by Jonathan Crusoe 1992 Jan 17 (Box 5)
- Memos & Itineraries regarding Parker T. Hart's Tours of Saudi Arabia 1961 Aug 16-1962 Dec 16 (Box 5)
- "Mission to Mecca: The Cruise of the Murphy" by John S. Keating 1976 Jan (Box 5)
- National Geographic article "Saudi Arabia: Beyond the Sands of Mecca 1966 Jan (Box 5)
- "A New American Posture Toward Asia" in Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Sciences1970 Jul (Box 5)
- News clippings 1948 Feb 13-1988 Mar 16 (Box 5)
- News clippings & magazine re the Persian Gulf War 1990 Nov 27-1992 Feb 27 (Box 5)
- News clippings re Francis E. Meloy, Jr. and Robert Keeley 1976 Jun 17-1980 Jun 1 (Box 5)
- News clippings re Kuwait 1963 Jun 19-1992 May 5 (Box 5)
- News clippings re Personal and Family Interest 1947 Mar 16-1967 Aug 12 (Box 5)
- News clippings re Saudi Arabia 1975 Apr 3-1996 Sep 23 (Box 5)
- News clippings re Turkey 1960 May 28-1989 Mar 13 (Box 5)
- News clippings re United Arab Emirates 1970 May 3-1991 Jul 10 (Box 5)
- News clippings re Yemen 1969 Oct 25-1990 May 23 (Box 5)
- Newspaper Articles re King Saud (all in Arabic) n.d. (Box 5)
- Oral History Interviews of Parker T. Hart 1969-1973 (Box 6)
- Paper Notes on Egypt and the Suez Crisis n.d. (Box 6)
- Papers & Articles on Middle East Oil Production 1980-1992, n.d. (Box 6)
- Papers & Articles regarding Parker T. Hart's Electronic Dialogue with the American Consulate General in Dhahran 1988 Feb 24-Apr 2 (Box 6)
- Papers & Correspondence regarding Kuwait and Parker T. Hart's visit 1961 Sep-1962 Dec 7 (Box 6)
- Papers & Notes regarding Operation Hard Surface and Bunker Mission ca. 1963 (Box 6)
- Paper re Kennedy, Nasser, and the Middle East by Douglas Little n.d. (Box 6)
- Paper re "Syria's Quest for a Regional Role" by Itamar Rabinovich 1986 Dec 11 (Box 6)
- Paper re "The Early Years of the Saudi State" by George Rentz 1977 Jun 16 (Box 6)
- Paper re the Central Treaty Organization (CENTO) 1969 Jan-1979 Mar 28 (Box 6)
- Papers re Meda'in Saleh Trip 1964 Feb (Box 6)
- Papers re Parker T. Hart's Commemoration Trip to Dhahran 1994 Oct (Box 7)
- Papers re Role of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers in Saudi Arabia 1988 Apr 26-1192 Feb 4 (Box 7)
- Papers re Syrian Embassy Study (copies) 1980 Jun-1980 Feb 26 (Box 7)
- Papers re the "Art of Diplomacy" by Christopher J. McMullen 1979 (Box 7)
- Persian Gulf Study Project 1982 Feb 10-Jun 30 (Box 7)
- Personal Correspondence of Parker and Jane Hart 1960 Aug 3-1993 Feb 11 (Box 7)
- Photographs--Snapshots ca. 1950, 1965-1967 (Box 7)
- Photographs--Large, including publicity photographs of Hart ca. 1945, 1965 (Box 7)
- Published Statements re the Termination of the Yemeni Crisis 1962 Dec (Box 7)
- "Qatar News" Newsletters 1976 Mar-1989 Jul (Box 7)
- Records of Foreign Relations Documents of U.S. and Saudi Arabia 1937 Jul 12-1946 Oct 22, 5 folders (Box 7-8)
- "Reflections on Saudi Arabia" by Parker T. Hart 1980 May 20 (Box 8)
- Report of Cartographic Projects in Saudi Arabia 1961 Oct (Box 8)
- Report on the state of Yemeni Health and Medical Institutions 1981 Mar-Jul 16 (Box 8)
- Representation, Guest Lists, and Notes of Parker T. Hart in Turkey 1965 Oct 9-1967 Jun 13 (Box 8)
- Reviews of Books & Articles on the Middle East 1948-1981, n.d. (Box 8)
- "Roots of a Partnership" Notes, Drafts, and Inserts n.d., 2 folders (Box 8)
- "Saudi Arabia and the United States"--Manuscript Chapter Summaries and a Draft of Part III, Chapter 8 1993, n.d., 2 folders (Box 8)
- "Saudi Arabia" Newsletters of the Saudi Arabian Embassy in Washington, D.C. 1984 Jun-1996 Jun (Box 9)
- "Saudi Hegemony in the Arabian Peninsula: Riyadh's Policies Toward Its Neighbors" by Brooks Wrampelmeier 1977 (Box 9)
- Scrapbook of News clippings in Arabic 1961-1965, 2 folders (Box 9)
- "Sun and Flare" Newsletters 1945 Oct 25-1967 Dec 6 (Box 9)
- Symposium on Muslim Law 1953 (Box 9)
- "Syrian Revolt of 1925" by Joyce Laverty Miller 1977 (Box 9)
- Timeline for the Ottoman Empire n.d. (Box 9)
- Treaties and Establishment of Relations between the United States and Yemen ca. 1946 (Box 9)
- "The Turco-Egyptian Flirtation of Autumn 1954" 1956 Nov (Box 9)
- Turkey--Printed material re 1971, 1989 (Box 9)
- United Nations Documentation of Relations between Kuwait, Iraq, and the United Kingdom 1961 Jun-1963 Oct (Box 9)
- United Nations Documents regarding Yemen Crisis 1963 Apr 29-1964 Oct 8 (Box 9)
- "U.S. Policy in the Middle East" by Parker T. Hart 1971 (Box 9)
- U.S.-Saudi Arabian agreement on establishing Diplomatic Representation 1932 Feb 2 (Box 9)
- U.S.-Saudi Arabian Defense Security Agreements 1951 Jun 18-1977 Feb 27 (Box 9)
- "The View from Riyadh" by Parker T. Hart 1979 Oct 25 (Box 9)
- 4 Foreign Service Appointment Certificates belonging to Parker T. Hart 1943-1958 (Oversize OS Box S-53)
- Large Map of the Arabian Peninsula 1963 (Oversize OS Box S-53)
- 7 Large Maps of Turkey and the Surrounding Areas 1947-1963 (Oversize OS Box S-53)